David Verhasselt

Senior Software Engineer, Contractor

Tallinn, Estonia & Ghent, Belgium

+372 559 59 633 🕿

david@crowdway.com ⋈

www.davidverhasselt.com

dverhasselt in

davidverhasselt >

dv 😱

Belgian, eligible for work in EU and UK willing to relocate

Profile

Senior software engineer with 5 years of professional web development experience on the back-end and front-end using **Ruby**, **Ruby on Rails** and **Javascript**.

I prefer BDD with Rspec and Capybara and am a big proponent of object oriented best practices like SOLID. I'm active in the open source community and regularly invest time in learning about the latest technologies and keeping my skills up to date.

Technical Skills

Extremely Proficient With

languages Ruby, CoffeeScript, JavaScript, HTML5, CSS3

technologies Rails, Rspec, Haml, Sass, Ajax, Git, Vim, Redis, PostgreSQL, Sphinx, Nginx, Facebook APIs, Google

APIs, Docker, Backbone.js, jQuery, Bootstrap, Stripe, Oauth

Have Experience With

languages Python, C, C++, PHP, Java, Bash & Zsh Scripting, Swift, Objective-C, Actionscript 3

technologies Scrum, Sinatra, Memcache, CDN, WebGL, MySQL, Elastic Search, Cocoa, Nginx, CUDA, Flex

Experience

2014–2015 Rails Engineer, PieSync, Consultant.

Ruby, Ruby on Rails, Coffeescript, Stripe, Ecommerce, Microservices, APIs

Built the Ecommerce subscription functionality for the PieSync SaaS service, integrated with Stripe allowing users to sign-up and pay, and expanded the customer-facing dashboard. Also worked on the internal back-end responsible for synchronizing different APIs. Helped integrate the platform with several different CRM APIs.

2013-present **Lead Developer**, *ICE Technologies*, *Consultant*.

Ruby on Rails, Google APIs, Domain Registrar APIs, Sphinx, Performance

In charge of gradually upgrading and adding features to the internal management and sales system. Added integration with Google Calendar and Google Contacts, and the ability to register domain names for clients from within the application. Greatly improved performance using memcache and Javascript.

2013-present **Lead Developer**, *Tightship*, *Consultant*.

Ruby on Rails, Sphinx, Elastic Search, Solaris, Performance

Managed to convert a poorly maintained codebase from Rails 2.1 to Rails 4. Improved performance from 12 seconds per page view to <3 seconds using code improvements and careful caching. Refactored away technical debt in line with the client's budget.

2007–present **Founder, Developer**, *Seenly*.

Ruby on Rails, Javascript, Facebook Graph API, Backbone.js, Scalability, PostgreSQL, WebGL

Photobooth-like web app. Created first version using Actionscript 3 and PHP, later completely rewrote it using Ruby on Rails, HTML5 and WebGL. Bootstrapped to 850K unique visitors a month with over 51 million photos taken to date. Integrated with Facebook to allow users to upload photos.

2014 Project Manager, Onio Technologies, Consultant.

Javascript, Ecommerce

Lead internationalization of sales webpage and added multi-currency and VAT-compliance using geo identification to the shopping cart.

2011–2012 Rails Engineer, Reverse Robocall, Consultant.

Ruby on Rails, Heroku, Telephony API, Spree, Authorize.net, Ecommerce

Built web app where users could purchase automated robocalls to politicians. Integrated Spree, a shopping cart environment, with Tropo, a Twilio-like Telephony API, to call users and record their message as part of the purchasing process. Automated sending hundreds of robocalls to politicians. Reverse Robocall was featured on Slashdot and Ars Technica.

2008–2010 Web Application Developer, Ghent University.

PHP, MySQL, Linux

Maintained and extended the internal administration web app used by over 100 student organizations.

2004–2008 **Sysadmin**, Student organization Zeus WPI.

Linux, Solaris, Sysadmin

2003 Freelance developer, Matrix Orbital.

Delphi, Microcontrollers, Embedded Systems

Open Source Contributions

Creator of the popular **redis-semaphore** gem which utilizes Redis to implement distributed semaphores as Dijkstra intended. It includes fail safety using timeouts to guard against client failures.

I have also made significant contributions to other popular open source projects such as Rails, less-rails, acts_as_tree and BubbleWrap. See my github profile for details.

Education

2008–2010 MS Computer Science Engineering, Ghent University, Belgium.

minor Information and Communications Technology

honors Cum Laude

2004–2008 **BS Computer Science**, *Ghent University*, Belgium.

Master thesis

title Affine Motion Compensation using Translational Motion Vectors on the GPU

supervisors Bart Pieters, Stijn Notebaert, Rik Van de Walle

Using CUDA I architected and developed an affine motion compensation process to be run on the GPU, and inserted it into a reference H.264 video encoder to improve video compression without sacrificing speed.

Spoken Languages

DutchExcellent (Native)EnglishExcellentFrenchIntermediateGermanBasic

Estonian Basic